It started with the social media account of a man who claimed
事情源自於一名男性的社群帳號
to have returned from the orifices.
他說自己成功從洞中歸來
The orifices lead to 200 years in the future.
洞的另一邊連結到兩百年後的世界
And it's not on Earth.
而且不是地球
The orifices led to a planet overflowing with brightness.
洞的另一頭是光輝燦爛的星球
I don't think the brightness was perceived through my eyes,
那種光輝應該不是肉眼看到的
but rather through my five senses,
而是用五官感受到的
since I could even see it with my eyes closed.
因為我就算閉上眼睛，仍然覺得耀眼
The brightness had a natural effect of making people happy.
待在光輝中自然就會變得開心
The place where people gather is different from a town but is beautiful.
雖然並非是城鎮
By the way,
對了
many people are already in this light-filled place.
已經有很多人置身在光芒之中
And there is no cell service that connects to Earth.
順便補充一點 地球的訊號在這裡不通
The word "return" gave rise to a lot of unfounded speculation.
自稱從洞裡“回來”的男人 引發許多沒有根據的臆測
Many other accounts appeared, which tried to enhance credibility
社群網站上出現許多帳號
by posting descriptions of photos claimed to have been taken in the orifices.
解說男人上傳的洞中照片 試圖提高可信度
However, it took less than a month for this man's lie to be exposed.
但不到一個月 這名男人的謊言就被揭穿
Not a single person has yet returned from the orifices.
至今從未有人從洞裡回來
After having recorded the stories of five people,
完成五個人的紀錄後
Okamoto remembered something.
岡本想起了一件事
His relationship with his grandmother.
就是他和奶奶的關係
He was wondering which part of his life would be appropriate to record
岡本在猶豫要記錄人生的哪個部分
for a life leading to the orifices.
才適合銜接在洞中的生活
Through the personal histories of the first five people,
他內心深處的煩惱根源
Okamoto's deeply rooted worry
在聽了五人各自擷取的人生歷程後
had grown large enough for him to clearly recognize it.
已經茁壯到足以清晰辨識的程度
This worry would eventually influence his final decision…
這份苦惱將會影響 岡本做出的最後決定
but that comes later in the story.
但那是後話
At this time, Sugaya was pondering on the option of not entering the orifices.
此時的菅谷心裡在想 不進去洞裡也是一種選擇
Upon thinking about the order of entry, he had realized something.
思考大家進洞的順序後 他發現一件事
If they followed their set schedules, Kawabata would go in first.
如果按照原定計畫 第一個進去的會是川端
Sugaya would be second.
第二個則是菅谷
He was afraid of being the only one in this group not to enter the orifices.
菅谷害怕自己會是這個團體裡面
In the absolute freedom where they could decide if they wanted to enter or not,
進不進去都是個人的自由 也不會有懲罰
Sugaya was binding himself with his own self-consciousness.
他純粹是被自我意識所束縛
Who's next?
下一個是誰？
Oh, me.
哦，是我
I was being ignored by my classmates for a short period of time.
有很短的一段時間被大家無視
It all started with a classmate of mine who played soccer.
起因是一個有在踢足球的同學
His name was Takayuki.
他叫崇之
I joined the same soccer club as him later on
我後來也加入和他一樣的足球俱樂部
and apparently, he didn't like that.
他好像對此事不太高興
Kawabata saw a certain similarity between himself and Shingo.
川端單方面地認為 他跟真吾的距離拉近了
It was their positions in sports.
是因為體育運動中的定位問題
Like Shingo, Kawabata had also struggled with jealousy.
川端也和真吾一樣曾為了嫉妒所苦
He had to deal with a good amount of unfairness,
他一直遇到許多不公平的事情 為此感到憂愁
yet he had never gotten angry.
不過他從未生氣
However, he would later come to realize that he was the exact opposite of Shingo.
不過川端待會就會知道 真吾和自己是截然相反的類型
Before I started playing soccer, I was a quiet kid at school.
開始踢足球之前，我在學校個性文靜
But after I began playing soccer,
但開始學足球之後
I gradually started joining in conversations in class.
我漸漸開始在班上和大家交談
Takayuki often said, "You used to be the quiet kid."
崇之經常抱怨 “你本來很安靜，性格怎麼變了？”
Let's go to the schoolyard.
要去操場嗎？
Okay. Dodgeball?
好啊，要打躲避球嗎？
Let's play against Class 2.
我們去跟二班比賽吧
With the soft ball?
用軟球一較高下？
The hard ball isn't good for curveballs, so I'll go inflate the soft ball.
硬球比較難丟出變化球 我去將軟球充氣
-Let's go! -Yay!
-走囉！ -好耶！
Shingo. Soccer quiz time.
真吾，足球問答時間到了
Uh, okay.
哦，好
What's an early cross?
什麼是“前點傳中”？
You don't know?
你不知道嗎？
No way! Have you been pretending to know soccer?
不會吧！你是不懂裝懂 你是自以為懂足球？
Hey guys, he's a pretender! Unbelievable!
大家聽我說 他是裝作很精通！有夠糟糕！
You're a pretender who's playing soccer. Gross.
自作聰明還敢踢足球，讓人反胃
By the way, I was better at soccer than he was.
順帶一提，我踢得比他好
You're so gross. Don't act so cocky, you pretender!
裝懂這行為讓人反感，少在那邊囂張
Since then, Takayuki kept telling the other classmates
從那天起崇之就不停地 對班上同學說真吾不懂裝懂
At first, none of the classmates listened to Takayuki.
一開始沒人理會
But due to his persistent ignoring of Shingo,
但看到崇之徹底無視真吾後
the classmates gradually started to follow suit.
同學們逐漸開始學他
At first, they weren't completely ignoring me.
一開始他們並沒有完全忽視我的存在
Morning.
早安
Oh, uh-huh.
哦，嗯
I started realizing that they were avoiding me
後來才發現大家都在躲我
but I kept talking to them as usual.
不過我還是繼續跟大家搭話
Let's go to the traffic park.
去交通公園玩吧
-Yes! -Yay!
-好啊！ -耶！
Hey, Akira. You're friends with Mocchi, right?
小晶，你和阿持很要好吧？
One day, Shingo decided to talk to Akira,
有一天，他和在班上不起眼
a quiet student who was good at basketball.
但籃球打得很好的小晶攀談
Until then, he hadn't talked much with Akira.
真吾在這之前和對方沒什麼交流
We play cards together.
因為我們會一起玩卡牌
What game do you play?
什麼卡牌啊？
A card game I came up with.
我想的卡牌
Wow, I'd like to try that too.
是喔，我也想玩玩看
You have to start by making your own cards.
那要從製作卡牌開始
But because you could make cards that are too strong,
但有可能做出太過強大的
you can't make them alone.
不可以隨便亂做
You have to make them with me and Mocchi.
要和我跟阿持一起製作才行
What kind of game is it?
哪一種的？
I have a rulebook.
有規則書
Ghost Bug Bird. Radiance of the Phoenix.
幽靈蟲鳥
Guard with Shadow.
-3000傷害！ -影之防衛
Megalo Monster. Illusion. 900.
梅加洛獸，顯現幻覺
Cursed Mask. Guard again.
詛咒面具，再防守一次
Here I go.
來囉，惡魔之手，攻擊力2200！
Ugh.
討厭
Why don't you get along with Takayuki?
你為什麼跟崇之不和啊？
I didn't have a problem with him.
我沒有跟他處不來啊
But in our soccer club, he gets scolded and I don't.
他在球隊一直被罵 但我沒有那麼常被罵
Actually, he's the quiet one on our team.
在球隊反而是他比較文靜
In my opinion, he's a pretender too.
我個人覺得啊，他也很愛裝懂
I'm not pretending to know stuff.
我又沒有不懂裝懂
Rock Arm. Attack…
岩石巨臂，攻擊力…
-Whoa! -Twelve hundred!
-哇！ -1200！
About four months after Shingo and Akira started hanging out together,
真吾和小晶的關係持續約四個月後
the other classmates who had been ignoring Shingo started talking to him again.
之前排擠真吾的周遭同學們 開始會和他說話
We want to play cards with you two too.
我們也想和小晶跟真吾玩卡牌
Shingo accepted this.
真吾接受了他們
As for Takayuki, he had stopped coming to school.
至於崇之 不知從何時起他就沒來學校了
I heard this from my parents, so I don't know the whole story,
這是我聽爸媽說的，不太清楚
but apparently Takayuki and his parents had to run from debt collectors.
聽說崇之和他的爸媽一起躲債去了
That's why he transferred schools without goodbyes.
所以好像沒跟學校說一聲就轉學了
To be honest, when I found out about this, I felt…
老實說，在我明白 他發生什麼事的時候
Happy's not the right word…
心中有種不同於開心的感情…
Well, I guess I was kind of happy.
不過算是有些歡喜啦
But I thought I shouldn't say it out loud.
但我明白不能跟別人說我很高興
After graduating from university, Shingo traveled around Japan and other countries,
真吾大學畢業後 在日本和國外四處旅行
searching for ways to make money on his own.
摸索靠自己賺錢的方法
Actually, I got a job after graduating from university
其實我大學畢業後先進了公司
but it got boring after three years.
在那裡工作三年後，覺得太無聊了
I probably didn't have to travel around the world
雖然不一定要去旅行
but everyone on social media seemed to be traveling.
但我看社群網站的大家都在旅遊
Shingo had started to think working with others at a company
真吾認為與別人一同進入公司 活在他人的嫉妒中
and living amid others' jealousy wasn't suitable for him.
不合自己的性情
I tried my hand at various things.
我做過各種嘗試
Like programming and things I could start my own business with.
像是寫程式等感覺有辦法創業的事
I did come up with new services and created apps
我想了新的服務模式 也製作了手機應用程式
but none of them caught on.
但完全沒人氣
Seeing other entrepreneurs I knew appear in the media,
看到認識的創業家陸續登上媒體版面
I felt the urge to start something new too.
我也覺得必須做點新的挑戰
Yet, everything new I tried to create failed.
但自行創作的新東西全都不管用
And this was what worked out for me.
唯有這工作算順利
-Here you go. -Thanks.
-這給你 -好
You'll handle it?
只要給你就好？
Yes. I will pay you once it's sold.
對，等賣掉才要匯款
Great.
了解
Okay…
好
-What account will you be using? -Oh…
-你是用哪個帳號？給我看一下 -哦…
This one.
這個
Let me take this.
我幫你拿
My proxy online sales business went fairly well,
代理上架網路商店的生意 進行得還不錯
and I started earning a small profit from it.
開始賺得到小錢了
An ad campaign I did on social media worked out well too,
我在同時間進行的 社群網站行銷成功了
and after six months, I managed to save up a bit of money.
持續半年後，存到了一些積蓄
My follower count skyrocketed too.
我的追蹤人數也暴漲了
Excuse me.
你好
I have an appointment. I'm SHINGO.
我是跟你約好的SHINGO
Using social media to attract customers is incredibly effective.
在社群網站吸引客人效果非常好
Yet, it won't work if the actual charm of an inn isn't there.
說是這麼說 若實際住宿的旅館不誘人就沒辦法
It's not enough if the place only looks appealing on the internet.
只在網路上看起來吸睛 卻虛有其表的話效果不會持久
On the other hand, it's a shame if an inn has charm
反過來說，旅館本身具吸引力
but isn't effectively promoted on social media.
但沒有在社群網站上被宣傳出去 真的十分可惜
Well…
可是啊
We have young staff who are managing a few accounts on social media.
已經有幾個年輕員工 在幫我們經營社群帳號了
Don't worry. I'm good at what I do.
請放心，我不會輸給他們
It hasn't made much of a difference.
我覺得沒什麼差吧
The question is, is that person a professional social media marketer.
社群網站的運用 重點在於是不是真的專業
On page 12, I have listed the performance of the accounts I previously managed.
12頁記載的是 我運用社群網站達成的實績
Shingo started a new business as a social media management consultant.
真吾開始嶄新的商業模式 提供社群帳號的運用諮詢服務
Let me introduce a Japanese inn
推薦給情侶
that is perfect for a summer getaway for couples.
介紹夏天來訪後滿意度高的旅館
It's surrounded by stylish spots that are totally photogenic,
附近有時尚景點，拍出來的照片超美
and it's also a foodie heaven.
也可以來一趟開心的美食之旅
The seafood at the inn is top-notch as well.
旅館的餐點和海鮮真的無可挑剔
And the ocean view from the window is seriously stunningly blue.
從窗外看出去的大海特別藍
On top of that…
而且現在…
If you mention you've seen this review on SHINGO's account,
只要說你是看了 SHINGO帳號的介紹來的
you'll get a free one-hour pass for the private hot spring.
就可以拿到私人溫泉一小時免費券
A Japanese inn that is perfect for a summer getaway.
介紹夏天來訪後滿意度高的旅館
Shingo's consulting services were successful once again.
真吾的運用諮詢生意也大有起色
The inn's clientele shifted to younger people,
旅館的客群轉換成年輕人
attracting a large number of visitors.
讓許多人前來入住
It quickly became a popular destination.
轉眼間就成為熱門旅館
I successfully promoted several hotels and guesthouses.
然後我從事 飯店和民宿策劃的生意很順利
The business itself finally got on track, and I made some friends.
事業終於步上正軌
-Hey, man. -Hey.
-你好啊 -嗨
Your hotel in Oita was quite the buzz.
大分那間飯店爆紅了
It hit my highest revenue ever.
創下至今最高的紀錄
You're making good money, huh?
看來你賺很多喔
I hope you're not gambling illegally.
你沒玩違法賭博吧？沒問題吧？
Nah, I'm clean.
我向來潔身自好啦
You might not have to make money anymore
雖說你可能已經賺夠了
but there's a call for PR proposals for a foreign-owned hotel.
不過現在有一間 外資飯店正在募集宣傳企劃案
Do you want to collaborate with my company?
想問你要不要和我的公司合作 去小試一下
Oh, I didn't know that. When's it due?
是喔，我都沒聽說，什麼時候的事？
We're working directly with the hotel, bypassing the ad agency.
因為我們跳過代理商 直接和飯店接觸
Is it legit?
那樣做沒問題嗎？
Well, it might be a bit…
這個嘛，可能算是…
special.
特例啦
Whoa, you're really pushing the envelope.
天啊，你野心真大
The presentation I prepared with Kondo was able to beat out other ad agencies.
後來我和那位近藤合作的企劃 贏過廣告代理商
That's amazing. How old were you?
好厲害，那是你幾歲的時候？
Um, I was--
我想想，記得是…
Matsuoka reacted to the term "ad agency."
松岡對“廣告代理商” 這個詞起了反應
That term had her momentarily wondering
她的腦海裡瞬間閃過
how many times she had been manipulated by those who bore that title.
自己以前被與此有關的人 任意擺布了多少次
She instantaneously had stopped listening to Shingo's story.
她頓時不再聽他說話了
So, I actually started working with the hotel's PR director.
然後啊，我們實際開始 和飯店的宣傳部長一起工作
I heard he's pretty nice, but that he'd drop me if the results were bad.
聽說對方出奇和善 但拿不出好結果會馬上被開除
The turnover is quick in rich foreign-owned companies.
-是外資又有錢的話換人速度會很快 -是喔
Excuse me.
打擾了
Come in.
請進
This is SHINGO.
這位是真吾
I'm SHINGO. Nice to meet you.
我是SHINGO，請多指教
I'm Sato.
敝姓佐藤
-Take a seat. -Thank you.
-請坐 -謝謝
So SHINGO, in the end, the inns and hotels you were managing were rural, right?
真吾，你之前推廣的 是鄉下的民宿和飯店吧？
Um, yes.
呃，是的
You might've been a star there, but I wonder how it'll be here.
你在他們眼中也許是個大紅人啦
You're pretty much a newbie.
你還是個毛頭小子嘛
Right…
是啊
How old are you again? Pretty young, huh?
你幾歲啊？還年輕吧？
Can you handle our brand?
有辦法善用我們的品牌力嗎？
I mean, our clientele is different,
畢竟客群的年齡也不一樣
and that age group doesn't use social media much.
我們的客人都不太會關注社群網站
But with this campaign, you're aiming to target a younger demographic, correct?
不過這次的活動 要主攻的是年輕人對吧？
Well, yes. But that doesn't matter much.
是這樣沒錯，總之不管怎麼說
All I need to see are results.
你拿得出好看的數字吧
My campaigns have been successful most of the time,
我辦的活動都有擄獲目標客群的心
so I just wondered if I can leave it up to you.
我只是懷疑是否真的能交給你
I see.
這樣啊，我會努力的
Well,
沒差啦，如果三個月內拿不出成果 到時我馬上開除你就好了
Thank you for your time.
告辭
-Yep. -Thank you.
-好 -先走了
He wasn't nice at all.
他哪裡和善了？
I heard he's usually a really nice guy.
-我聽說他平時人很好 -是喔
Great news for young people
手上沒多少錢
who want to stay at a resort hotel but don't have much money.
卻想要住度假飯店的 年輕人和情侶，我有好消息
That famous luxury hotel is starting an amazing campaign
那間高級飯店 居然要針對從來沒住過的人
for those who have never stayed with them before.
提供超級划算的優惠活動
The signboard might've already given away a spoiler.
看這個招牌就已經猜到了吧
-Details about the hotel are at the end-- -Hold it.
-看到最後就能知道飯店的詳情… -等一下…
-Oh. -Come.
-過來一下 -好
So…
我問你喔…
What are you going to do with that?
你打算拍那種片做什麼？
First, I'm going to edit it to target couples and upload it.
我會先編輯並上傳 一部針對情侶的影片
Will it achieve it?
那樣會成功嗎？
Achieve what?
你的言下之意是？
High views.
就是指數字啊
Look, my campaigns are always successful.
你想想，我都能成功打中客人的心
Instead of uploading these short videos online,
不需要拍那種不正經的短片 上傳到網路
I could teach you a more effective way.
我可以教你更直接的成功方法
I think I mentioned this in my presentation.
可是當初的企劃案就是這樣寫的啊
Yeah, so?
是喔，所以呢？
You want me to do something different?
你現在是要我改嗎？
It's not about doing something different.
這不是改不改的問題
May I continue filming, then?
那我可以繼續拍嗎？
It's not that.
重點不在那裡啦
I want someone who listens to me.
我要的是能聽我的話做事的人
Not being flexible about changes
你沒有臨機應變的能力
shows that you still have the mindset of a student.
看來還擺脫不了學生的思考模式
Your videos have never hit it big, have they?
你從來沒有成功過，甚至沒被我認同
Sorry…
對不起
You have no idea how quickly I got promoted.
你不知道我升職得多快吧？
I got to this position in no time.
我出社會不久就做到這個職位了
Instead of relying on social media,
不要用什麼社群網站
you should reach out to the media.
你該多去聯絡媒體
Just tell them, "PR director Sato is making a move."
說是“佐藤部長的指示” 凡事都可以馬上搞定
I see…
明白了
This is the buffet.
這裡是自助餐的場地
One, two, three, four, five, six…
一、二、三、四、五、六…
Although it's a buffet,
明明是自助餐 當場為客人現做的廚師有十三人
Here is the buffet.
這裡是自助餐的場地
One, two, three--
一、二、三…
One, two, three, four, five, six…
一、二、三、四、五、六…
Although it's a buffet, there are 13 chefs who will cook for you on the spot.
明明是自助餐 當場為客人現做的廚師有十三人
This is a surprise even for me!
連SHINGO也嚇了一跳啊！
The rooms have large windows with a panoramic view.
房間裡有扇能眺望美景的大窗戶
And even the bathroom! Voila, ocean view!
就連房間的浴室居然也有海景可看！
Yeah, no.
嗯，果然不行
We can't use this. It's not suitable for our clientele.
這部不能公開，不適合我們的客群
For the younger clientele--
年輕的客群…
No.
總之不行，完全不行啊
None of Shingo's videos were released during the contract period,
真吾的影片 在合作期間沒有公開任何一支
and the contract ended.
合約就這麼到期了
Six months later,
在半年後
Shingo received a phone call.
真吾接到一通電話
Hello?
喂？
Mr. Sato, the PR director, apparently passed away from a stroke.
聽說宣傳部長的佐藤先生 因腦梗塞過世了
I was wondering if you'd like to attend his funeral.
我想問你會不會去參加喪禮
No way, I'm not going.
不，我不可能去啦
Why not?
為什麼？
Why would I?
這還用問？想也知道吧
After I endured all that power harassment and unfair criticism,
他一直對我職權騷擾，專挑我的毛病
he practically broke the contract.
還找理由讓我的合約作廢
Yeah, but he died.
可是他已經死啦
So what?
死了又怎樣？
What he did to me won't disappear.
我遭受的對待不會就此消失
I can go on bad-mouthing him without a problem.
我現在還是敢說他的壞話
Don't be so petty.
不要那麼小肚雞腸嘛
I'm petty? What do you mean petty?
什麼？誰小肚雞腸？我嗎？
You know exactly what happened.
你也知道他對我做了什麼啊
Yeah, but he's already dead.
是沒錯，可是對方都已經死了
What do I care if he's dead?
所以說死了又怎樣？
Does being dead suddenly make him above criticism?
人死了就偉大到 什麼都不能批評了嗎？
Huh?
你說話啊
Why won't you answer?
不說話很了不起嗎？
You're not grateful to him at all?
他不是對你有恩嗎？
Nope, not at all.
才沒有，絕對沒有
Okay, yeah.
好，明白了
I do understand your sentiment too.
我也能體會你的心情
But aren't you being petty?
但那樣不是很小心眼嗎？
I mean, it would be nice if I could live without holding grudges.
我自己也覺得 如果能不帶任何仇恨而活就好了
I know people like that exist.
實際上有些人也是那樣
But whether you can forgive someone just because they're dead is
但這和他死掉之後我要不要原諒他
a separate issue.
是兩回事吧？
Calling you petty makes it sound like it's your problem.
還說人小心眼 好像是你氣量狹小的問題
Right?
你也這麼覺得吧？
Well, yeah.
是啊，總之呢
Towards the end, I was just complaining
最後雖然有點在發牢騷
but that's my story.
不過故事大概就是這樣
I hope no one has to experience that.
我希望以後不要再遇到這種事
Before entering the orifices, Shingo posted his last social media post.
真吾在進去洞裡前 發了最後一篇社群網站的貼文
In his post, he wrote that he would be entering the orifices.
報告他即將進到洞中
And also that, if someone was holding a grudge against him,
另外提及如果有人恨自己 希望能在他啟程之前
he would like to talk to them before entering the orifices.
當面談一談
Subtitle translation by: Mariko Yasuoka-Sator
字幕翻譯：劉翠恬
Apartment number 813!
813號室！
Why are you shouting out the apartment number?
為什麼要喊房號？
We wanted to see the corpse.
想看屍體…
Want me to find out?
要我查打工的地方嗎？
I'm not interested in your curiosity.
我對你的好奇心沒興趣
Seven Orifices.
《驚天七洞》
This was the first time I regretted it.
當下我第一次感到後悔